<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Supplement to His Majesties most gracious speech directed to the honourable House of Commons / by the commons of England.</title>
            <author>Wagstaffe, Thomas, 1645-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96510</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W217</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42908</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875927</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875927</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152478</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96510)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152478)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2298:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Supplement to His Majesties most gracious speech directed to the honourable House of Commons / by the commons of England.</title>
                  <author>Wagstaffe, Thomas, 1645-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Wagstaffe by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Commons.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152478:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Supplement to his Majeſties moſt Gracious SPEECH.</head>
            <head type="sub">Directed to the Honourable Houſe of Commons, by the Commons of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO add to the Works of the greateſt Men, if the Nature of the Subject permits or requires it, hath never yet been thought an immodeſt Undertaking, nor prejudicial to the Honour of the firſt Author. You are now moſt about the <hi>Ardua Regni,</hi> and indeed more Arduous Matters never yet came before your Honourable Body. It is not therefore to be conceived that Things of ſuch a great and various Nature ſhould be all ſumm'd up in a <hi>ſhort Speech;</hi> nor is there reaſon to expect that the King ſhould charge his Memory by a long recital of Particulars how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant ſoever they may be, and neceſſary for your Inſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. We therefore in all humility, in the Name of all the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> make bold to lay before you ſuch Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Matters which ſeem to us to be of the greateſt Weight, and abſolutely require your Conſideration, and your grave Wiſdoms to apply ſome ſpeedy and effectual Remedy, and which are either but ſlightly touch'd, or wholly pretermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the King.</p>
            <p>We confeſs indeed that the King has laid the Scene very large, and wide, when he reckons our Misfortunes, and the Miſcarriages that have been this laſt year, according to this Diviſion, <hi>Such as have been upon Land, and ſuch as have been
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152478:2"/>at Sea.</hi> This Diviſion is comprehenſive, extends to all the Calamities we groan under, and if you pleaſe to examine what hath been acted, or what hath been defective for want of act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, on theſe <hi>Two Elements</hi> according to the full Latitude of theſe Expreſſions, you will not fail to diſcharge the Truſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in you, and to ſee the Cauſe and Occaſion of all our Miſeries.</p>
            <p>But however the King hath been ſo large in the General, we conceive he is not ſo expreſs in Particulars; which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we humbly crave leave to ſupply and lay before you, by a juſt and impartial Repreſentation of ſuch Inſtances, which nothing in the World can obſcure, palliate, or excuſe; And out of Deference and Reverence to his Majeſty, we ſhall do it according to the ſame Diviſion. And we ſhall begin with the latter.</p>
            <p>Such <hi>Miſcarriages as have been at Sea.</hi> Theſe have been ſo terrible that they make all our Hearts ake; the <hi>Merchant</hi> feels the immediate ſtroke, but the influence extends all over the Kingdom. The Loſs of the Effects (how great and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ſoever) is the leaſt of the Evils; The whole Trade is in danger to be loſt, or mightily diminiſhed. The indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Merchant is exhauſted, and diſcouraged; many have not the Ability, and many not the Will, to venture any more their Intereſts under that unfortunate and impolitick Conduct, they have already ſo often, and ſo dreadfully miſcarried. The King calls this a <hi>Diſgrace,</hi> and indeed it is ſo, but if that was all it was no great Matter; the Merchants we ſuppoſe could bear the <hi>Shame</hi> well enough, if they had but their Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects: And if ſuch <hi>prodigious Loſſes</hi> affect only the <hi>Modeſty</hi> of the Nation, we are pretty well yet; we may <hi>bluſh,</hi> or ſo, and the harm is over. If the Merchants interpret that which hath ſuckt out their very Hearts blood, to be only ſome <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace</hi> to them, we preſume they are the <hi>modeſteſt</hi> Men living.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152478:2"/>However, let the <hi>Diſgrace</hi> be what it will, that might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired again, by an honourable Action; But as the caſe ſtands this is irreparable, our Honour and Intereſt are both ſunk to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. The moſt beneficial Trade we have is almoſt, if not altogether, ruin'd; and that apparently by ill Management. The Winds and the Storms the Merchant bears patiently, and his Loſſes redouble his Vigour and Induſtry: But when he is ruin'd by his <hi>Guard,</hi> when he is <hi>convoy'd</hi> into Deſtruction, this admits of neither Remedy, nor Hope; and there is not ſo much as Chance or Contingency to encourage him: And every Man will conclude 'tis time to give over, and to ſit ſtill, rather than to fraight his Ships for the Benefit of Enemies, and run the Riſque of ſuch deſperate Adventures. The King tells you, That <hi>Trade is Eſſential to the Welfare of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> Then our <hi>Welfare</hi> is loſt with our <hi>Trade,</hi> as being <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential</hi> to it, and the moſt flouriſhing Kingdom in <hi>Europe</hi> is reduced to Barrenneſs and Penury. Our Money is gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad already, and if our Trade, which ſhould ſupply us with more, is gone after it too, we have nothing left but to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment our Miſeries, and with that ſtinging Aggravation, that they are irrecoverable. The Commodiouſneſs of our Ports, the Skill of our Merchants, the Expertneſs of our Sea-men, (all the Coſt in the World) will ſtand us in no ſtead, but to make us more unhappy. All the Advantages are poyſoned in the Conduct, and made the Inſtruments of our Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</p>
            <p>But here the King tells you, <hi>That he hath Reſented it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly, and that he will take Care that thoſe who have not done their Duty ſhall be Puniſhed.</hi> It may be ſo; but here we crave leave to add this <hi>Supplement,</hi> That we hope this will not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, nor abate the <hi>Reſentments,</hi> nor take off the <hi>Care,</hi> from bringing the Offenders to condign Puniſhment. The King's <hi>Reſentments</hi> and <hi>Cares</hi> ought to be a ſpur to yours, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152478:3"/>by yours will do two great things at once, both imitate the King, and conſult the Safety of the Nation; and in order to this, we humbly propoſe theſe following things as highly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving your Enquiry.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How it came to paſs, and by whoſe means, that the Merchants, after ſo many Petitions and Addreſſes, were for ſome Months detained, and no importunity could obtain ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Convoy or Leave to proſecute their Voyage. And they were reſerved to that <hi>Critical Time,</hi> when the <hi>French</hi> Fleet were juſt ready and prepared to receive them. If the <hi>French</hi> themſelves had had the Conduct of our <hi>Fleet,</hi> they could never have timed it better; they are no ſooner got into the <hi>Streights,</hi> but our <hi>Smirna</hi> Fleet is ſent into their Mouths. Put theſe together, that the Merchants were ready many Months before, and all the Application they could make could never procure Liberty, but they muſt go <hi>then, juſt then,</hi> when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could hinder them from falling into the <hi>French</hi> hands. And we ſhall leave it with any conſidering Man, whether it be poſſible to believe but there was Treachery in the caſe, at whoſe door ſoever it will lye. And it is not for nothing, that our Fleet was ſcarcely out of ſight, bur there was a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Report about the Town, that it was in danger to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the <hi>French.</hi> Which evidently proves, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers of their going out were privy to te Secret, and knew well enough what would become of them. To this may be added.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What was the Reaſon, and who was in the Fault, that our <hi>Grand Fleet</hi> which ſet out with them, did not ſee them out of danger? Was the <hi>Grand Fleet</hi> deſigned only to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement Sir <hi>George Rook,</hi> and the Merchant-men, and to bring them ſo far on their way, and wiſh them a good Voyage? If this were all indeed, they did their Parts, and a <hi>Gun</hi> at parting would fully execute their Commiſſion. But if it was
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152478:3"/>to protect them from the <hi>French</hi> Fleet, what fair Reaſon can be given that they left them ſo ſoon, or that they left them at all, till they were ſure they were clear of danger? Was it upon ſuppoſition the <hi>French</hi> Fleet was not out? This is a fine Conduct indeed, to leave matters of this Conſequence to Gheſſes, and Suppoſitions. The Merchants had ſtaid long enough, and there were <hi>Frigets</hi> enough and to ſpare, to have ſent to <hi>Breſt,</hi> if the matter had been doubted. And we are in a fine Condition, when matters of ſuch importance muſt be managed by uncertain Conjectures; and when our prime Miniſters neither have good Intelligence, nor will give ſuch Orders, whereby they cannot fail of it. But we believe this is not the Fault; and any Rational Man, who impartially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders this Conduct, will conclude, That the Suppoſition was on the contrary hand, and it was ſo fatally manag'd, upon the Suppoſition the <hi>French</hi> were out, rather than upon Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition that they were not.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another Miſcarriage deſerving your Enquiry, is, That after this woful Loſs, and the exact Knowledge of it, our <hi>Grand Fleet</hi> again ſet ſail; Who was in the Fault that they did not directly ſail to the <hi>Streights,</hi> and repair our loſt Honour upon our Enemies? The <hi>French</hi> Fleet was then foul with their long Voyage, ſome of their Ships diſabled, and the Fleet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly weakened, ſo as they were in no good Condition to reſiſt the force of our Fleet, which was freſh, and ſo well pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared. This might have redeemed our Loſs, at leaſt have compenſated it. But inſtead of this, we do nothing but ſail ſome Leagues to Sea, and then return; as if the Buſineſs of our <hi>Grand Fleet</hi> was for nothing elſe but to make a <hi>Flouriſh,</hi> to ride in triumph over the Waves, but not to fight with our Enemies. And ſurely it is matter of Enquiry whoſe Fault was it that this promiſing Opportunity was loſt? Was it for want of Orders? Or for not executing them? Or for want of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152478:4"/>Stores and Proviſions? Each of theſe are unpardonable Miſcarriages, and will lye ſome where, and we hope your Wiſdoms will ſearch this to the bottom. For 'tis a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table thing, that the Treaſure of the Nation muſt be thus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed away; that our Navy muſt be rigg'd at incredible Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, and all for nothing elſe but to <hi>furl their Sails,;</hi> if the Buſineſs of the Fleet be only <hi>Shew,</hi> and not <hi>Action,</hi> we think a <hi>Paſt-board</hi> Ship at my <hi>Lord Major's Shew</hi> might do as well as any in the Ports, and ſave the Nation a great deal of Money in their Pockets.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Notwithſtanding all this, and that our Fleet hath hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been from home, the <hi>French Privateers</hi> have been more buſy and bold than ever; they lye perpetually on our Coaſts, take our Veſſels out of our Harbours, and ſometimes in the very Sight of the <hi>Fleet.</hi> And what does our <hi>Fleet</hi> ſignify that can ſecure us neither at home nor abroad? Heretofore we uſed to boaſt of our <hi>Wooden Caſtles,</hi> as the Strength and Defence of our Countrey. And the Truth is, our <hi>Ships</hi> and our <hi>Sea-men</hi> are as good as ever, but if they are made unſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable and uſeleſs by ill <hi>Conduct,</hi> 'tis all one to have no <hi>Fleet</hi> at all, as none to defend us.</p>
            <p>For the Cloſe of this, the King tells you, <hi>It will deſerve your Conſideration whether we are not defective in the Number of our Shipping.</hi> And intimates his deſires that you would ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that defect; but except you ſupply the defect of <hi>Conduct,</hi> you may provide as many Ships as will bridle the Ocean, and juſt to as much purpoſe as thoſe you have already. And the Truth is, we have Ships and Men enough, but our want is more <hi>honeſt and able Miniſters:</hi> And if we muſt lay out our Money to ſupply <hi>the Defects of the Navy,</hi> let us do it where the need lyes, and purchaſe <hi>wiſe and faithful Managers.</hi> And we know no Reaſon why <hi>Our</hi> Money may not buy <hi>faithful Counſellers,</hi> as well as the <hi>French</hi> Money can buy <hi>treacherous.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152478:4"/>ones. In ſhort, if you make Proviſions for the Navy, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to begin at the right end, to provide us <hi>juſt and skilful Ministers of State:</hi> For let the Ships and Commanders be what they will, while they muſt act under the direction of <hi>corrupt and ſelfiſh Miniſters,</hi> we can never hope to be better. This is an Error in the firſt Concoction, and can never be rectified; in vain therefore do you provide <hi>Ships</hi> and <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies</hi> if you do not take care of the <hi>Helm,</hi> and ſee that ſuch <hi>honeſt Guides</hi> are ſet up who will mind their Country more than themſelves, and the publick Intereſt more than their own.</p>
            <p>The next Branch of the Diviſion is the <hi>Miſcarriages</hi> (the King calls them the <hi>Diſadvantages</hi>) <hi>at Land.</hi> And theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are by no means <hi>equal to,</hi> becauſe they are ſar greater than theſe <hi>at Sea.</hi> The Loſs of <hi>Heydelberg</hi> and <hi>Reſes,</hi> of <hi>Huy</hi> and <hi>Charleroy;</hi> beſides the terrible Defeats in <hi>Two pitched Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles,</hi> the one in <hi>Flanders,</hi> the other in <hi>Piedmont:</hi> In all which, beſides the Towns and Caſtles, the Artillery and Baggage, the <hi>Confederates</hi> loſt very few leſs than <hi>Fifty thouſand Men.</hi> But to come to that in which have we were more immediately concerned, and that is the Battle at <hi>Landen;</hi> of which the King tells you. That it <hi>was only occaſioned by the great Number of our Enemies, which exceeded ours.</hi> Now we cannot deny the Truth of this; for it is unaccountable, that an <hi>equal</hi> or <hi>leſs</hi> Number of Men ſhould ſtorm a Camp, and make ſuch terrible Havock and Slaughter, and take moſt of the <hi>heavy Cannon and Baggage.</hi> But this notwithſtanding, there are Two things to be added by way of Supplement.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How it came to paſs, that at that Battle, the <hi>French</hi> came to exceed ours in <hi>Number?</hi> The Confederate Army were 80000 Men, and if they had been kept in a Body, or near together, they would have equalled, if not exceeded, the <hi>French.</hi> But by a new <hi>Martial Policy,</hi> a great Detachment
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152478:5"/>was ſent away under the Duke of <hi>Wirtemberg,</hi> and another greater to cover <hi>Liege</hi> and <hi>Maeſtricht;</hi> and then, when our Army was weakened, the <hi>French</hi> ſought and beat us. And what better could be expected? 'Tis in vain here to ſay, we did not think the <hi>French</hi> would attack us, but that they would direct their Courſe towards <hi>Liege</hi> or <hi>Maeſtricht;</hi> for that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of mending the Matter makes it worſe, and the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages greater. For 'tis inexcuſable in a <hi>General</hi> to ſay, he did <hi>not think of his Enemies; Non licet in belio his peccare.</hi> And 'tis a greater Dishonour to a <hi>General</hi> to be ſurpriz'd and taken unawares, than to be beaten: For Victory is an Act of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, but the other is his own Negligence, or want of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. The Engliſh of this is, <hi>Luxemburg</hi> outwitted us. And we are like to have a fair Account, when our Enemies are ſtronger in their <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Arms.</hi> The King tells you, <hi>'tis neceſſary to augment our Forces,</hi> and hopes you will accordingly ſupply him; but according to the Meaſures of the laſt Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers Campaign, 'tis impoſſible to know what <hi>Numbers</hi> are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. For you muſt not only provide a <hi>ſufficient Number</hi> to fight, but a <hi>ſufficient Number</hi> alſo to be <hi>ſent away.</hi> And what Number or Purſe is ſufficient for both theſe Purpoſes, we doubt will puzzle your <hi>Arithmetick</hi> as well as ours.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The other thing we crave leave to add, is, The unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable Conduct of removing our Camp, in ſuch a Juncture, from a ſtrong and well fortified Place, to pitch it in a <hi>Plain;</hi> one would have imagined, when our Army was ſo much weakened, a little foreſight would have taught us to keep in the ſtrongeſt Hold; had we continud in our Camp at <hi>Park Abby,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> would have found it a tough piece of Work to have forced it: And <hi>Luxemburg</hi> knew it, and therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic'd us out, and made his Advantage of it. But this is not all; We are not only contented to relinquiſh a Place of Strength, but we muſt encamp ſo awkardly as to place a <hi>River behind
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152478:5"/>us;</hi> whereas any Man, who had the experience, but of one years <hi>Campaign,</hi> would eaſily have ſeen the incommodiouſneſs of ſuch an Encampment. And that the <hi>River</hi> ought to have been <hi>before</hi> and not <hi>behind</hi> us; both to hinder the Approaches of the Enemy, and, in caſe of Defeat, to ſecure a ſafer Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat; and the Event plainly proved it, to our Coſt. For the Situation of our Camp gave far eaſier acceſs to the <hi>French</hi> than they could have had, if they had been to approach us over a <hi>River;</hi> and upon the Victory the <hi>River</hi> ſerved not only to barr a regular Retreat, but made even the confuſed Flight far more deſperate. And it had theſe Two fatal Effects; to keep us longer under our Enemies Swords, and to drown our Men when they fled from them. And in truth, the <hi>River</hi> deſtroyed far more of our Army than the <hi>French</hi> did, or could do. There is great Reaſon therefore that you ſhould <hi>augment our Forces,</hi> that you may be ſure to have enough to make <hi>Bridges,</hi> to ſecure the Retreat of the reſt.</p>
            <p>And thus much we thought good humbly to add, with reſpect to the <hi>Martial</hi> Miſcarriages: But there are others of a <hi>Civil</hi> Nature, and God knows theſe are not leſs Fatal to the Welfare of our Nation; it deſtroys us at home, as theſe do abroad. We need not go into <hi>Flanders</hi> for our Deſtruction. We have <hi>Cankers</hi> and <hi>Moths</hi> in our own Bowels, which conſume us as effectually as our Enemies Swords. There is no doubt but you will have Complaints enough from all Quarters, and the Miſeries this poor Nation labours under will reach your Ears from all parts of the Land, and we hope you will relieve them. We ſhall therefore ſelect a very few, out of that great Number, to repreſent unto you.</p>
            <p>And the Firſt is, The misimployment of our Treaſure: Our Money is ſpent contrary to the Ends for which you gave it. This is plain to a Demonſtration, you gave laſt year <hi>Five Millions</hi> to deſray the Expence of this years War; a Sum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152478:6"/>ſufficient, and to ſpare, and more than ever this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom before paid in one year; and yet neither our <hi>Sea-men,</hi> nor our <hi>Land Forces</hi> are paid. A Proclamation was iſſued ont to continue the <hi>Sea-men</hi> in pay all the Winter, which is only to multiply an unneceſſary Charge, and without the leaſt Advantage; but this was only to prevent the Murmurings and Complaints of the <hi>Seamen,</hi> but this will not do; for the Crys of their Families, and their own want of Bread, makes them deſperate, and their Complaints fill the Ears of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of all Men beſides. Their Wives and Children live upon Truſt, in hopes of Repayment when the Summers Expedition is over; but now their Creditors are weary of Truſting, and will give them no more Credit, as having no proſpect when they ſhall be paid. And this is the ſtate of moſt of our <hi>Sea-men,</hi> and 'tis diſmally ſad that they muſt ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their Lives, and <hi>themſelves and their Families</hi> be ſtarv'd for their Pains. The Caſe is not one jot better with the <hi>Land Forces:</hi> They have neither <hi>pay nor ſubſiſtence Money.</hi> And to give you one Inſtance for all; in the <hi>Tower Hamlets</hi> ſome hundreds and Quartered, and they liv'd ſo long upon their Hoſts that they both Grumbled, and upon the ſame Reaſon, for <hi>want of Pay,</hi> one from the <hi>Government,</hi> the other from the <hi>Souldier;</hi> inſomuch that a Fortnight ſince, my Lord <hi>Lucas,</hi> (no doubt by ſuperiour Direction) ſent the Officers of the reſpective Pariſhes to all the Publick Houſes, acquainting them, That if they would Truſt each Souldier as far as 35. a Week, he would be reſponſable, and ſee them paid.</p>
            <p>This is Demonſtration that our <hi>Forces</hi> are not paid; and they muſt either ſubſiſt upon <hi>Truſt,</hi> or upon <hi>Freequarter,</hi> or <hi>Periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is not only the Caſe of the <hi>Souldiers,</hi> but of all other Perſons concerned relative to the War. Thoſe who have fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed Naval Stores, and Arms; the Work-men who belong to the reſpective Yards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they are all in the ſame Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152478:6"/>and have no hopes, but the Expectation of <hi>what you will give.</hi> And now let us ask, If any mortal Man can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that <hi>Five Millions</hi> was not abundantly ſufficient to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fray the whole Expence of this year? nay, Whether the one half of it be not more than ſufficient? And yet the <hi>publick Debts</hi> ſtill increaſe upon us, and by a ſtrange <hi>State Paradox,</hi> the more you give, the more you owe. By this Rule, your Supplies will but ſet us further behind hand; for if <hi>Five Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions</hi> have run us ſo much in Debt, what will <hi>Ten Millions</hi> do? In ſhort, you may give what you will, but without ſome ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Care, and more than hath hitherto been taken, the Iſſue will be always the ſame; for if when you have given more than enough, the Forces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not paid, neither will they, if you give Ten times more. For when our Money is once diverted into a wrong Channel, the ſame Stream will carry away all we have, and with the ſame eaſe and ſecurity. This therefore is an unſufferable <hi>Grievance,</hi> in whoſe hands ſoever it lyes; and is no leſs than robbing the Nation, and abuſing your Supplies. Give us leave to ſpeak a <hi>ſad</hi> but a <hi>plain Truth;</hi> if any <hi>Pentioner</hi> Pockets up any of the Publick Moneys, he does not only betray his Truſt, and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, but he devours the Blood of the <hi>Souldiers</hi> and <hi>Sea-men,</hi> and feeds upon the Spoils of the People. The Eyes of all the Nation are upon you in this particular: And if you do not make a ſtrict and impartial Enquiry into this laſt years Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, they will be tempted to think, what ſome do not ſtick to ſay, not only that you do not care what becomes of our Money, but that you dare not dive too deep into the Accounts, leaſt your own Names be found there; and you are forced to connive at other Mens Guilts, leaſt you diſcover your own. We therefore earneſtly pray you, for your own ſakes as well as ours, that <hi>before</hi> you give any more Money you will carefully examine the Publick Accounts, and ſee firſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152478:7"/>what is become of the laſt. That you will diligently inſpect through whoſe hands it paſſed, to whom diſpos'd, and for what uſes? And we do not doubt but you will find at the leaſt the one half of it imbezled, or miſapplied; and we hope you will not only detect and puniſh whom you ſhall find Guilty, but make them refund, and reſtore alſo, what in plain Engliſh they have <hi>ſtolen</hi> from the Nation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Exportation of Corn in a time of Scarcity, or (which is all one) to make a time of Scarcity. Wheaten Bread is now in <hi>London</hi> 12 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi> a Buſhel, and White Bread 18 <hi>s.</hi> and Corn all over the Kingdom bears ſome Proportion to this, and riſes in the Price, reſpectively to the different Places; and is Three times dearer than uſual, eſpecially conſidering the ſeaſonable Harveſt. And this is plainly the Effect of Expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; and we have <hi>Dutch</hi> Factors all over the Nation, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Markets, and ſtarving the Poor. And we cannot but take notice of a late Proclamation, both here and in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> forbidding under ſtrict Penalties to tranſport Corn to <hi>France;</hi> which is a pleaſant Buſineſs, when 'tis already, by Act of Parliament, made Treaſon to correſpond there. But this Proclamation has two Edges; the one was to lay the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium of the Dearth upon we know not who, <hi>Jacobites;</hi> as if all the Corn had been by their means tranſported into <hi>France.</hi> And this hath been Artificially and Induſtrioufly ſpread through the Countries; but this had like to have ſpoil'd the Project, for the Countrey took the Alarm, and was glad of any occaſion to keep their Corn at home, and roſe unanimouſly to defend their Corn from <hi>French Harpies.</hi> But upon ſecond thoughts, it was judg'd convenient to ſend ſome Souldiers to the Ports, and other Places, to keep the People in order, and patiently to ſee their Corn carried away before their Eyes. From whence 'tis notorious enough, that our Corn goes to <hi>Holland,</hi> and not to <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152478:7"/>
            <p>And accordingly the other End of the Proclamation is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to encourage the Tranſporting it to <hi>Holland.</hi> A Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>France</hi> is a tacit Direction to <hi>Holland.</hi> It had not been very plauſible, nor perhaps ſafe, to have ſent out Orders for the Tranſporting Corn to the <hi>Low-Countreys,</hi> but this might be done as well by a ſide Wind; 'tis but proclaiming that none muſt be ſent to <hi>France,</hi> and then the Inference is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, there is no danger in carrying it to <hi>Holland;</hi> nay, not to leave the matter to Inference and Collection, there are po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive and direct Orders, in the Ports of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> not only to permit the Factors for Corn to Buy and Ship it, but are ordered Convoys to guard them to <hi>Holland.</hi> From whence we plainly ſee from what Quarter our Scarcity comes, and what great Compaſſion we bear to the Poor of <hi>England.</hi> Let the <hi>Dutch</hi> have but Plenty, and it is no matter if our <hi>Poor</hi> be Starv'd. We need ſay very little in this particular to awaken your Diligence in examining it; nor what great Care our Laws have taken to preſerve equal the Prizes of Corn, by the Proviſions they make againſt <hi>Reſtrators, Foreſtallers,</hi> and <hi>Monopolizers.</hi> For if you do not take ſome Care, and that ſpeedily too, the Poor will carve for themſelves, as they have already in ſome Places: Hunger breaks through Stone Walls; and if Famine comes on us, by your neglect, you muſt thank your ſelves, if the Poor fill their Bellys at your Coſt, and eat up what you had provided for your own Meals.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Corrupt Adminiſtration of Juſtice. This is the worſt Crime in a Commonwealth: A Murtherer, or Thief, breaks the Laws; but a Corrupt Judg both breaks and debauches it, and poyſons the Fountains of Juſtice. Do we not daily ſee the <hi>Judges</hi> acting under the Directions of the <hi>Miniſters of State,</hi> as if a <hi>Judg</hi> was ſworn not be guided by the <hi>Laws,</hi> but by the <hi>Secretaries.</hi> The poor and ſcandalous Acts of picking up, and cheriſhing the moſt profligate Villains to make <hi>Evidences</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:152478:8"/>of; as in the Caſe of <hi>Fuller, Holland,</hi> &amp;c. The intolerable and illegal Fines; when a Man not worth a Farthing ſhall be Fined Two or Three hundred Pounds, contrary to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Law, which always limits Fines to Mens Abilities, and with a <hi>Salvo contenemento</hi> of this every Seſſions gives no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Inſtances; and particularly the laſt, when one Mr. <hi>Cooke,</hi> upon the ſingle Evidence of <hi>a Beggar, and vagabond Papiſt,</hi> and that Evidence not direct to the Fact neither, but only by hear-ſay; for ſhe ſwears ſhe ſaw him ſet a Seal, and heard Mrs. <hi>M.</hi> ſay, it was the Seal of my Lord <hi>N.</hi> and this is all that came up to the Indictment; and yet upon ſuch an Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the Man was found Guilty, and Fined 200 <hi>l.</hi> and Mr. Recorder, by wonderul Eloquence, made him believe the Court did him a favour in not ſetting him in the Pillory. And is not this, think you, an admirable Courſe of Juſtice, when an Evidence by <hi>hear-ſay</hi> ſhall be ſufficient to convict a Man? And if you pleaſe to conſult the Records of the Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, you will find a great Number of ſuch ſhameleſs Caſes. Perhaps it may be ſaid here, that the Perſons convicted ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were, or were ſuſpected to be <hi>Jacobites,</hi> and ſo no Friends to the Government, and no matter what became of them: But we are not Pleading for the <hi>Jacobites,</hi> but for Juſtice; and Juſtice is blind, and knows no Parties. And we preſume un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der former Governments (when theſe things were complain'd of) the reſpective Perſons under ſuch Sentences were not thought to be Friends to the reſpective Governments. If the Adminiſtration of Juſtice is limited to Perſons and Parties, and not to Things and legal Proofs, 'tis partial, and corrupt; and we are not governed by the plain Rules of Law, but by Faction and Paſſion.</p>
            <p>But if this was the worſt, and ſuch partial diſtributing of Juſtice concerned only the Subjects Liberty and Property, it might be the better borne. But in the Caſe of Life it is juſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152478:8"/>the ſame; theſe Men make no more to Hang a Man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law, than to Fine him. The Caſe of Capt. <hi>Aſhton</hi> you all know, and there hath long ſince an Opinion been given of it in the <hi>Houſe of Peers:</hi> But there is a freſh Inſtance of one <hi>Anderton,</hi> a Printer, who was Murther'd by the Bench againſt the plain Words, and expreſs Direction, of the Law in that very Caſe made and provided. The whole is very well worthy your Notice; but we ſhall not take up your time with mentioning the want of One, much leſs of Two, direct Evidences to the Fact charg'd upon him (which the Law ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly requires in the Caſe of Treaſon) nor the indirect means to induce the Jury to find him Guilty, by <hi>Brow beating, Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> and ſuch like; which ſo over-awed the Jury, that moſt of them brought in a Verdict directly contrary to their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. To omit theſe, which deſerve your Enquiry; the ſingle Queſtion is, Whether <hi>Printing be Treaſon,</hi> according to the Laws of <hi>England?</hi> He was indicted on the Statute of Treaſons, 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. Now 'tis as plain as the Sun that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting could not be Treaſon, by the expreſs Words of that Act; for Printing was not in uſe, nor known, when that Act was made: And it is to be remembered that that Act limits Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and expreſly declares, that there ſhall be no Treaſons for the future but what are there expreſſed, but what ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in Parliament. If it be ſaid, though it be not there expreſly, it is vertually, and by interpretation: But pray what kind of Treaſons are thoſe which are virtual, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretative Treaſons? Our Laws know no Treaſons by infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and conſequence, but what are plain and expreſs in the Law. But whoſe Interpretation is this? The Interpretation of the Judge, or of the Law? The Judge hath interpreted it ſo indeed, and hath hang'd a Man upon it, but the Law hath interpreted it quite otherwife; and the Law is ſo far from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting Printing to be Treaſon, that it hath plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152478:9"/>that it is not ſo, and conſequently not within that Act. The ſtatute 14 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. hath made Proviſion for the very Caſe, hath taken notice of and aſſigned Puniſhments for the <hi>Printing Seditious Libels,</hi> and ſome of them hath left to the Diſcretion of the Bench; but with this negtive Clauſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, <hi>not extending to Life.</hi> This is a plain Caſe, that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Seditious Libels is not interpreted Treaſon by the Law, but the contrary; and if it be not Treaſon by the Conſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Law, then by the ſame Conſtruction it is not Treaſon within the Statute of Treaſons. For the Fact is not expreſs in that Statute, nor could be; the Queſtion is only concerning the Conſtructon of it, and the Law hath already conſtrued it not to be Treaſon, <hi>as not extending to Life.</hi> So that the Conſtruction of Law, is in direct oppoſition to the Conſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Judge <hi>Treby;</hi> and he hath hang'd a Man in downright contradiction to the very Words of the Law. Now 'tis to be remembered, That this is Law, of Printing, is your own; and you have made it your own Act, by reviving it; and to have your own Laws invaded openly before your Faces, is ſuch an unparallel'd Boldneſs, that no Words can ſufficiently expreſs; and in the Caſe of Life, 'tis Murther beſides. We are no Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of <hi>Seditous Libels;</hi> Let the Printers of them be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, but then let them be puniſhed according to Law, and not by Arbitrary Conſtructions and Wreſtings, which will ſerve (if the Judge be ſo diſpos'd) to hang any Man in the World: For if he conſtrue one thing to be Treaſon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the expreſs Words of Law, he may by the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon conſtrue another thing to be ſo; and ſo at length our Lives and Properties ſhall not be judged by juſt Laws, but by unjuſt Men.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole; If the Current of Juſtice be ſuffered to run in the ſame Channel, no Man is ſafe, your ſelves are as obnoxious as others; for when once you come to be out of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152478:9"/>Parliament, and the Seſſions is over, you are equally liable to the Laſh of theſe Men with our ſelves. You may make what Laws you pleaſe, but if you do not take care that they are more honeſtly Exccuted, your good Laws will ſtand you in as little ſtead as they do us. The <hi>Engliſh Laws</hi> indeed are the beſt in the World, but if they are adminiſtred by the worſt of Men, we re never the better; there is nothing more mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful and tender, in the Caſe of Life, than our Laws, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the favourable Conſtruction and Latitude that the Caſe can admit of; but if they ſhall be crampt and pincht by a corrupt Judg, to the deſtruction of a Priſoner, what good does the Equity and Favour of the Laws do him? Our Laws are ſo very averſe to <hi>Cruelty and Bloud,</hi> that they will not permit a <hi>Butcher</hi> as a Jury-man to paſs upon Life and Death; but what does that ſignify, if <hi>Butchers</hi> ſhall be permitted to ſit upon the Bench.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Poſture of <hi>Foreigners</hi> within this Kingdom. This is a matter of high Conſequence and requires a ſtrict and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Eye, not only of your ſelves, but of every <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> beſides. <hi>Foreigners</hi> have always a ſeperate Intereſt from that of the Nation; and if for Numbers, or upon any other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, they become formidable, 'tis high time for the <hi>Natives</hi> to look to themſelves, and to provde for their own Safety and Security. This Kingdom hath already ſmarted under Two fatal Inſtances; the one of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> the other of the <hi>Danes;</hi> who being reſpectively called in, upon the pretence of Aſſiſtance, ſo ſoon as opportunity was ripe, made themſelves Maſters of the Country, kill'd our Princes and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and made the reſt their Slaves and Vaſſals. The Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of this continues freſh among us, and is proverbially tranſmitted to Poſterity; and ſo long as the Name of <hi>Lord Dane</hi> remains, will never be forgotten. And our own dear bought Experience, one would think, ſhould teach us Wiſdom
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152478:10"/>in this Caſe, and make us beware of Foreigners, and careful how we truſt them. Now we need not remind you, that a great part of the Military Force of this Kingdom is in the hands of Foreigners; moſt of the Commanders of the Army are Strangers to us, know not our Laws and Conſtitution, nor have any kindneſs for them, but have, muſt have Ends of their own divided from that of the publick Welfare of the Nation, and People. Give us leave here to wonder, and let all the World wonder with us, That the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Bench</hi> in the <hi>Houſe of Lords</hi> ſhould not only <hi>Vote</hi> for this, but make <hi>Speeches</hi> in defence of it. It was a ſmart Reply made by a noble Lord, <hi>That he might in a ſhort time ſee Dutch Biſhops in that Bench as well as Dutch Officers in the Army:</hi> That our Souls might as ſafely be committed to their care, as our Lives, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and Eſtates. And in truth if we give the Sword in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hands, which governs all things, we may ſoon have not only Dutch Biſhops, Dutch Presbyters, and Dutch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders; but Dutch Lords, Dutch Commons, and Dutch every Thing; and <hi>Lord Dutch</hi> may become as formidable to us, as <hi>Lord Dane</hi> was to our Anceſtors. For 'tis as clear as the Light, give them Power to defend us, and they have Power to ruin us; and thoſe who will Fight for us only for their Intereſts, will Fight againſt us upon the ſame Induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and if they can find their Account in it, we may ſoon feel the effects of their Valour, in ſubduing us, when they are not able to maſter our Enemies. A fat Morſel is good prey to a Souldier of Fortune: And if he can make his Fortune at our Coſt, we muſt own our ſelves beholding to him, if he does not carve liberally for himſelf, though it be upon our <hi>Bones and Carcaſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if you pleaſe to conſider the Poſture of Foreigners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, you will find not only that moſt of our Troops are compoſed of our old Task-maſters the <hi>Danes,</hi> and of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152478:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Dutch,</hi> and the <hi>French Refugees:</hi> But, (which extreamly ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens this Conſideration) that there are alſo a great Party of Foreigners in the heart of the Nation, who may ſoon be, if they are not already, prepared to ſecond any Attempt, if not to act in conjunction with them. This Inference is ſo natural, that nothing but the utmoſt Forgetfulneſs of our ſelves can make us careleſs on that hand: But if there be violent Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions, nay, apparent Evidences, that ſome great Matter is brewing among them, 'tis no leſs than deſperate Infatuation to lye ſecure and negligent under ſuch treatning Dangers in our own Bowels. It is not unkown to you how great a Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber there are of <hi>French Refugees</hi> in and about this City, who are in full Union with their Brethren in the Army; nor what Military Authority and Power the Duke of <hi>Lemſter,</hi> their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryman, hath in this Kingdom; nor can it be doubted but he hath great Authority and Influence over them, and manages them according to ſuch Methods and Councils as may beſt anſwer the Ends which are driven at. That accordingly moſt of the <hi>French Refugees,</hi> who are able to bear Arms, are actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Arm'd and Liſted under diſtinct Officers, and of whom the ſaid Duke is Chief. That there have been ſeveral Sums of Money diſtributed to them, and ſome in particular by the ſaid Duke, in all probability to ſupply themſelves with Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, to uſe upon ſuch Occaſions as they ſhall be call'd to when Opportunity ſerves. That, in purſuance of this, ſeveral thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Arms have been made and bought up by them; and that in particular one Gunſmith in the <hi>Minories</hi> contracted with ſome of the <hi>French Refugees</hi> for 500 Caſe of Piſtols, of a ſize ſhorter than Holſter Piſtols, and which he accordingly made, and half of the Money was paid him before hand, and the reſt at the delivery of the Piſtols. And that other Gunſmiths in the <hi>Minories</hi> had full Imployment from the ſame hands, in the ſame Work; and 'tis ſaid they have not bought up leſs than
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152478:11"/>8000 of theſe Caſes of Piſtols. It is here matter of your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Conſideration, what uſe theſe kind of Piſtols are to be put to? It is certain they are not for Imployment in the <hi>Field.</hi> And it is as certain they are ſitted for the Work they drive at; and we ſhall leave it with you, whether it does not por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſome ſudden and ſecret Execution, of a barbarous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? That accordingly ſeveral threatning Speeches have been given out, That ſome Perſons at a certain time ſhould have their <hi>Throats Cut;</hi> and ſome of them are grown to that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, as to make particular Threatnings; which ſhews they are almoſt ſure of their Deſign. A <hi>French</hi> Miniſter ſent ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Letters to a very conſiderable Clergy-man, threatning him, <hi>That he was a dead Man; That he was to buy a Halter for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; That there was a Gallows prepared for him, which he muſt firſt aſcend and mount.</hi> Further yet, That there have been not long ſince 700 Tickets, of myſterious Figures and Characters, ſcatter'd about St. <hi>Anns</hi> Pariſh among the Habitations of the <hi>French Refugees,</hi> and thrown into ſeveral Houſes, which plainly import ſome ſecret and myſterious Deſign. And, to cloſe up all, there are almoſt every Week great Numbers of <hi>French Refugees,</hi> and other Foreigners, brought over hither from beyond the Seas, on pretence to go and inhabit in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who notwithſtanding are kept in <hi>England,</hi> and no doubt to augmet their Forces, and ſtrengthen the Conſederacy.</p>
            <p>And now, Gentlemen, you that are the Truſtees and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives of your Countrey, we intreat you impartially to reflect what theſe things mean? Is it not apparent that a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is hatching, and a great Storm gathering; which, when it breaks, may overwhelm you and your Poſterities, if not prevented? Is it poſſible for you to believe your Lives, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and Eſtates, ſafe in ſuch Circumſtances? Did ever a wiſe Nation ſuffer Foreigners to become formidable in their own Countrey? Look into the Records of Time, and ſee if
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152478:11"/>there be one ſingle Inſtance in the whole World, where <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> had gain'd Power and Force enough, they did not make uſe of it to advance themſelves, and ruin the <hi>Natives?</hi> Was there no viſible ground of Jealouſy, the very Nature of the thing would alarm your uttermoſt Caution: And you have beſides that the Experience of all Ages, to quicken your Councils in this Caſe. But when Men of ſeperate Councils, Meaſures, and Intereſts from yours, when they are arm'd with Power and Number too; when there is apparently a bold Deſign actually ſorm'd, and run through the whole Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in ſuch a Caſe, the Danger is brought home to your own Doors; and 'tis high time to awake out of Sleep, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply your utmoſt Wiſdoms to the providing a ſpeedy and effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Remedy.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We have but one thing more to trouble you with, though it may not ſeem <hi>Grievous</hi> in the Nature of it, yet in the Conſequence it may be a more dreadful <hi>Miſcarriage</hi> than any of the reſt; and if you do not Remedy this, you can Remedy none of the other; and that is, <hi>The Poſt-poning the Redreſs of Grievances, to the giving Supplies.</hi> This is lodg'd in your own Houſe, and you have hitherto fatally laboured under it; you your ſelves know, by the Experience of your former Seſſions, and all the Kingdom knows, that ſo ſoon as you have given our Money, the Court hath done with you; and our <hi>Grievances</hi> remain the ſame, or grow greater, and you riſe <hi>re infecta;</hi> you have done the Buſineſs of the <hi>Court</hi> indeed, but not that of the <hi>Countrey;</hi> and ſo your great <hi>Truſt</hi> is but half executed, and the leaſt half too. The Queſtion therefore here is not concerning the Nature of Things, or the Preference of one before the other, (though yet we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Redreſſing our Grievances is every way as neceſſary to our Welfare as, if not preferable to, the giving Supplies) but concerning the <hi>Order of Time.</hi> We pray you let that be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152478:12"/>done <hi>firſt,</hi> which otherwiſe will not be done at all. We are ſure the <hi>Court</hi> will permit you to ſit to give Money: And we are as ſure you will not ſit to Redreſs our Evils, if you give that <hi>firſt.</hi> Money will be welcome firſt, or laſt; but our Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances muſt be remedy'd firſt, or never. Let your Time there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be ſuted to the Occaſions. Firſt examine the State of the Nation; conſider the Miſcarriages at Sea, and Land; and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply effectual remedies to the reſpective Miſeries we groan under; and then we ſhall more chearfully part with our Money.</p>
            <p>And thus we have preſumed to lay before you ſome part of thoſe manifold Miſcarriages our unhappy Nation hath lately felt, and ſtill feels the ſmart of; and which we humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive highly require your Conſideration. We hope this humble Addreſs will not be unacceptable to you: And we are ſure we have herein done our duty to God, to your Selves, and to our Country. However, if our humble Supplication will not deſerve the <hi>Thanks of the Houſe,</hi> we perſwade our ſelves the ſubject Matter of it will deſerve <hi>your Care;</hi> which is the utmoſt Aim of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Petitioners, THE <hi>COMMONS of</hi> ENGLAND.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
